[Music]
I'm very excited about this conversation
I have butterflies before each each time
we we speak who anticipating
anticipating it was was very it was
germinating for me it when I was walking
this morning I and I had been a trouble
wisdom yesterday doing all this work I
actually ran the deal logos workshop and
you know talking with Jordan hall and
with Nora Bateson and so and then all
that was in my mind and then all the
work that Chris and I have been doing
and then our previous dialogue about
soul all of that just sort of came
together for me and so I wanted to
propose something to you I don't know if
you got a chance to read that email I
said yes and III love the idea that you
might have a theory about Hans Hans or
something to do with beauty right yeah
well no I what I want to do is so I have
two I have two motives for this Mayo two
reasons I think they're more than just
motives I think they're going to justify
them I think they're reasons so what is
I think it's an argument that's designed
to try and not completely answer your
questions but leave at least give an
integrated way of it answering the
questions that you posed so I thought it
would act as an excellent platform for
the discussion because it's gonna talk
about beauty and soul and do logos all
of that great um and and then what I
also wanted to do was I wanted to start
playing and I mean in serious playing
with you know what does argumentation
look like now within dialectic right
what does that look like because right
now we're doing a lot of this other
stuff and like we can talk a little bit
later about you know what we would I did
in the workshop if you want and at all
and it's all great you know you do this
amplification and you're doing all this
work and I was already getting people to
start moving off of propositions into I
proposed that and you know and that kind
of move but I also want to try and start
playing with okay but what did like what
cuz argue argumentation like deal
dialectic is not for closure right and
it's not about coming to a conclusion so
what
argument Asian have so what the thought
that came to mind is exactly what I'm
proposing here that the an argumentation
is kind of like a setting forth of a
platform that is supposed to you know is
supposed to lead to something beyond the
argumentation as the dialectic unfolds
well it is I wanna maybe I can just step
back just a little bit haha and say that
our last conversation was about I
proposed this notion of soul yes and I
asked you to speak about that and then
John came up with the idea of reinvent
EO but you have the Latin word for
reinventing and and reinventing which
also means discovering right yes have I
got that right and I also wholly
rediscovering because these notions are
very old
so what we're inventing and we're
discovering at the same time and I then
after our conversation I thought geez we
could reinvent everything you know a
soul we can reinvent beauty we can
reinvent the world you know I don't mean
to be inflationary but it's like if
we're moving into a new paradigm we have
to reinvent how we see practically
everything right that's exactly right
and you I think we inventio is one of
the central functions of dialectic it is
we invent here that's a reanimation if
it's going to be a meta psycho
technology it has to be able to reinvent
you all over the place if it's going to
be effective and functional for us I
think that's I think that's a pivotal
point you just made there I don't think
it's inflationary at all I think the the
right the job of this is is to exactly
allow us to return to where every we
want to speak and find how to reanimate
it and bring it bring the logos to it
because all these concepts become
lifeless and innocence and they become
clichés and they become truisms and they
stop meaning something and yet we have a
sense that they're deeply meaningful on
some level but but we stop we stop using
them in any meaningful function and the
only way we could bring them back is by
let's say redefining them well I like to
also is not just redefining the words
it's redefining how we see the world
yes yes and and and we and reforming
ourselves in the face of that well what
kind of transformation do we have to
undergo to conform to the reality that's
being disclosed because whenever there's
a disclosure there's also a demand on us
in that we need to conform to that new
disclosure if we're gonna realize it and
so I think what I want what I think
you've provided me a good way of
reframing what I was saying earlier I
think there's a better way of saying it
I want to try and reinvent you
argumentation so that it's no it's no
longer what it has become which is you
know you know just the logical coherence
of propositions in order to just
establish a conclusion that's supposed
to defeat your enemy I want to try and
understand what was going on in this
Socratic use of argumentation because
very often those arguments don't come to
conclusions in fact the arguments
devolve into something else yeah and the
problem perhaps with arguments generally
as yeah as you say the rival risks yeah
they're painful
whereas I probably a good argument if
you come into the right spirit probably
has some kind of a joy associated with
it if the two like people are having a
wrestling match
you know you might disagree but I think
we're afraid to kind of disagree and
we're in the social media age we're
afraid to wrestle with each other on
some level so you know the plato's use a
nickname because he was it means broad
shoulder because he was a wrestler late
on right I'm a martial artist and so
yeah the point I was saying this in the
workshop yesterday the point is not
being right the point is to come into
right relationship both with the topic
and the other person that's what respect
originally met respect spec t arrest to
see the thing properly it doesn't mean
the same thing as a uni B and I said
what we're trying to do is steer a
middle path a very Buddhist notion
between merely attacking people or
merely agreeing with them we're trying
instead to afford each of us getting to
a place where we can't get to on our own
right because if we have too much
agreement then we fall into a bubble of
some kind yes yes you know and
very dull and and cliche but if we're
too antagonistic then we just you know
then it's just bloody blood everywhere
and well nothing that's nothing we don't
develop friendships and and that kind of
thing well there's no conduction to
respect and I want to I want to reinvent
yo that because it's also been
trivialized by some of the social dusts
just as discourse and but notice again
to resonate with another topic we're
going to hopefully bring into discussion
today notice how both agreement and
antagonism lead to an ugliness of speech
right the one is the ugliness of dead
conformity the ugh the other is the you
know the ugliness of confrontation and
threat and again trying to instead get
back to what it is to beautify speech I
want it I want I want to try and get
argumentation that and Kris and I were
talking about this is like that but my
thinking isn't set and then I speak it
to convince you it's instead as I try to
articulate to you my thoughts my
thoughts I'm actually reinvent yelling
my thoughts that in speaking them I
discover something in the speaking that
I didn't have before I spoke them to you
that's what I'm really trying to get out
so this red metaphor mm-hmm the rest
thing metaphor works well for that
purpose too because if you think every
particular proposition every proposed
speech Act and the way that you and I
have talked about it John makes a
particular space in the interaction and
so the entire form of the dialogue is an
act of spatialization right that you
test the spatial awareness of your body
even as you exert and are exerted by
your dialogic partners so the co plates
or the co creative act is actually an
act of of using the form of embodiment
in this case the embodiment of speech
itself as a way of making exploratory
space to then venture ever further ever
further ever further into that space and
definitional discussions are interesting
for that reason because if we're
thinking of the definition of a term as
a multi vocalist soul or dialogue or
love or any of the things that we might
be able to to put into this arena and
then
rest with our really it's I think it's
helpful to think metaphorically of each
of these definitions as spaces in which
to play that the definition is something
to be inhabited in order to then Illume
more territory around it as opposed to
something that we treat as as leading to
a fixed point of closure I think that's
exactly right because and that's where
so cuz when I was doing the workshop I
tried to move people I made people
actually engage in the speaker to
remember that proposition originally
comes from the speech octave I proposed
which is not the same thing as this is
the case right very different things I
try to bring that back out with it's
it's the Metin it's the it's the
metonymy again right everything is put
for something greater put for something
beyond it so everything if there's an
acknowledgment that every proposition
every gesture in the dialogue is
abbreviated knowingly and
self-consciously abbreviated then it
always has its eye fixed beyond its
point of meaning mmm beautiful yeah yeah
so it never becomes reified or stuck
yeah and and and there's always a living
force moving through it which again I
think all of these things keep coming
together in my mind which leads to soul
and beauty because yeah well because
what has soul is is what it what is
alive right what is what continues to
move through us and and what is
beautiful is also what is alive inand
what what is meaningful and not what is
stuck and frozen and broken and
fragmented and and ugly and right know
that I didn't mean to that this is I I
just was you I was excited when you said
you know all of these things are coming
together in your mind because that's the
original meaning of logos bring things
together so that they come to belong
together and that's something much much
more than what we've reduced it to logos
is the basis of our word logic and we've
reduced that to a coherence between
propositions but what you were talking
about there Andrew about how things come
together so they belong together and
they're in sold together and
live together that's the meaning of
logos and logical coherence is only one
aspect of that much richer manifold
right so we're trying to reinvent logos
yet all right to mean something not not
in this narrow logic just a logicians
kind of game and we're also trying to
what about what about my friend
Alexander always talks about mythos and
pathos as well sure that those those two
kind of work together so mythos is the
story is the the formal form of the
story and pathos is the deep sort of
feeling aspect to it and and if you get
if perhaps if we get too hung up on
logos we lose we lose our sense of
feeling and if we get too hung up on
mythos you know the story becomes too
sealed or closed or I'm making sense
here and that all those three need to
work together logos mythos and pathos
and that's what makes go for it yeah
okay I'll go ahead I'm just gonna say
but that's that's the point of the like
when you're doing the dialectic when you
want reading one of the dialogues the
like you know discipline ik I think it's
really important to do Harlan and others
have made you you don't pay attention to
just the argumentation the argumentation
is where you see the putting forth of
propositions but the drama is where you
see a putting forth of ways of life and
drama is exactly where the mythos and
the pathos you that's why that's why
Plato does his philosophy in dialogue
because it's only in dialogue that you
can get the wedding of the of the drama
and the discourse so smoothly together
hmm yes yes exactly
and only in and only in the
dramaturgical context can logos to have
a questing character yes there is an
implicit narrativity to the dialogues
precisely because there's a quest right
and that's where the dialogues are such
a beautiful marriage of the logos and
the mythos because the characterization
of the quest of logos is implicit to the
function of the dialog itself yeah the
questions which are propositional are
actually just the affordance of the
speech act thinking
of questing that's exactly the right way
to put it Chris I think that's really
good yeah hmm so shall shall I begin
some of my proposals please please ya
know maybe maybe let me go through sort
of sort of the four main things the
proposals and then we can go back and
trace through it a however you gentlemen
wish to well and then we'll just follow
as Socrates often says we will follow
the argument wherever it goes okay so
the first thing I wanted to do was I
wanted to bring up the connection so I
want to first of all make clear to
everybody who might be listening that
andrew was very kind to send a set of
questions and I thought originally I was
just gonna think about how he's gonna
answer each question better than I I
thought maybe what I should do is try
and logo so I should try and draw them
together into mutually supporting
proposals and so the first so Andrew had
some questions and he's just also spoken
earlier about you know connections
between beauty and soul and so I want to
pick up on our previous discussion about
this idea of the reinvent EO of soul as
that which mediates Mattacks ooh is that
the alog in between us between more
nests and suchness quite a bit about
that
the mediator yeah yes it was the
mediator like I don't know if you know
this movie metropolis this fairy look
what I do you're talking you talk to the
mediator as the guy who brings together
the head and the heart brings together
the hearts oh yeah yeah Don has a big
poster of Metropolis it's given me the
original like a print of the original
poster from metropolis that movie just
sings to me repeatedly so yeah it's a
beautiful illusion Andrew thank you for
that
okay so always thinking about and so
when we come back and review the first
proposal
I was thinking especially what you said
because Andrew about Hans book I'm
saving Beauty because I also think it's
a really important work and so we can
come back to that but I was thinking I'm
sorry been thinking a lot about beauty
and of course because it plays this very
important role and beautification we
than the dialogues and so I was trying I
was thinking about the correlation
between soul and beauty that you were
making Andrew I want to unpack that in
this proposal so I want to propose to
you that there's a continuum there's a
continuum in our experience in right and
now I'm doing a tone us attention right
there's a continuum between experiences
that emphasize suchness and experiences
that emphasize more Ness so overwhelming
more Ness is horror right and then a
little little less overwhelming is awe a
little less overwhelming is wonder now
let's go on the other side when you're
really picking up on the suchness people
express that with this positive term of
intimacy I know you intimately alright
and then if that's taken a little bit
deeper you people talk about being at
peace with each other and then even more
deeper a sense of being at home with
someone and you know Chris what I'm
doing here I'm picking up on right home
and horror has aspects of the sacred
right black veil indeed bar we get that
thing where right it's all it becomes
too enclosed right when I'm proposing to
you is the following beauty is that
sweet spot it's the sweet spot on that
continuum it's kind of a meta optimal
grip right it's it's the tone us between
being alive to the more nest and wonder
and being alive to the suchness and
intimacy and this is picking up on
scara's notion that when I encounter
something beautiful I both get a sense
of wow they she gives the example of the
tree right all right you come across a
beautiful tree I didn't know trees could
be like that there's a sudden more nests
but this tree is also not like any other
tree it has a suchness to it an
individual to it that is right
non-repeatable there's a hereness
announced that's precious
so the intimacy gives a preciousness of
you will allow me not sorry it's not my
golden when I shouldn't write to them to
the morning so the mortise is not an
abstract conception it's it's presence
right into the suchness so you see what
I'm trying to do Andrew here I'm trying
to propose to you that the
faculty of soul that mediates between
more nests and suchness is actually the
Faculty of the reception of beauty that
because beauty is the aesthetics the the
forming of our sensibility that's
finding that sweet spot between the more
nosov wonder and the intimacy of such
nests and so I think that picks up on
scurries notion of how beauty is
actually a deep kind of training for us
ok so that's the first proposal the
first proposal is that there's a deep so
I'm trying to I think you had a really
important insight there Andrew and you
see what I'm trying to do and trying to
propose I don't unpack it and that's
what the argument is doing it's saying
here's some things that I think come
from that unfold from that so that's the
first proposal is that ok yeah here's
the second proposal the second proposal
is a notion of wisdom that I get from
Socrates though of the relationship
between wisdom and virtue that each
virtue is just a particular way of being
wise in a particular kind of situation
so being wise in this situation is to be
courageous to be kind in this so to be
wise in this situation is to be kind to
be right so the idea is that virtues our
particular instantiations pick
particular ways of fitting right to
particular context so now making use of
Aristotle's notion of you know a virtue
always being between too much and too
little mm-hmm no now I'm gonna try and
draw them together here's the logos in
the proposal I think that wisdom has a
has a more Ness aspect to it a
self-transcendent aspect and the Greeks
had a word for this aspect of wisdom
this was Sophia this is the mourners but
they also had another word that's often
translated as wisdom and we've lost this
right in our translations as we
translate them both by the same word
they had phronesis and phronesis was the
ability
fit yourself well to a particular
situation right so Sophia is the morning
and you see what I'm doing here it's the
ability to pick up and resonate with the
more Ness phronesis is the ability to
pick up and resonate with the suchness
very small and the very big well it's
the urges it's the most intimate and the
most comprehensive okay yeah so then the
house of envious
so let me a spell so the espousal of
particular virtue in fitness to a
particular situation is precisely the
furnaces dimension of wisdom that's
right right but it Ignace the fitting
ness of that's right but the picking up
on how there's always so much more
behind any aspect of wisdom right that
there's so much more to being kind that
what then what just happened here that's
the Sophia because the kindness that I
show towards Andrew is not the kindness
that I show towards my son and it is not
the kindness that I show towards my
partner or the kindness I show towards
my student right there's more to
kindness but notice that's the Sophia
but being kind to Andrew in the right
way as distinct from how I'm kind of
Spencer right that's the phoniest did
that work did that make sense
mm-hmm absolutely so now I can put these
two together virtue is the beauty of
wisdom because Verte beauty is to get
the more nests it's a sweet spot between
the more nests and the suchness and
wisdom right is virtue is where you
bring the more nests into the suchness
that's what virtue is so virtue is the
beauty of wisdom virtue as this is why
Plato says you start first by looking at
the beauty of physical things and then
what the physical things in have in
common and then he moves this move which
many people have promised serious but he
and goes to say then you consider the
beauty of virtue but that's because
that's the move that gets you in that's
the best the form of beauty that is
particular
wisdom and this is the beautification
this is the kind of beauty that we're
trying to make right in dialectic okay
so that's the third proposal that virtue
is the beauty of wisdom so this leads me
to the fourth proposal and you see how
this is so this is right that this is
also an instalment process ender this is
exam --all taneous lis right because
virtue virtue it is again that process
of mediating appropriately between war
and the Sun mm-hmm okay so dialectic
here's the proposal the fourth proposal
notice how this is not a strictly
logically coherent argument it's an
argument but it's at logos argument on
gathering things together and then
gathering together and gathering
together right dialectic is the
beautification of thought in speech in
order to conform to virtue and this is
how we practice wisdom so dialectic is
the beautification of thought and speech
in order to conform to virtue and this
is how we practice and wisdom what does
this imply dialectic is about virtue in
two senses virtue is always the topic of
every dialectic and it is every dialogue
is about a virtue it is look the topic
and it is the enacted tonus we are
supposed to be talking about courage in
a dialogue but we are also supposed to
be enacting courage and Socrates always
exemplifies that in fact the enactment
of courage takes precedent over right
the topic anything that is spoken about
courage the speaking and the enactment
right the topic and the tono's are
wedded together because the ultimate
goal is to conform to virtue to love the
beauty of wisdom so that's that those
are the four proposals okay I have one
question about the word virtue because
it seems to be a word that's been kind
of abused and it has a moralistic tone
to it
that's actually a bigger word than that
it's it's a more virtuous doesn't mean
being goody two-shoes or something you
know it doesn't mean just being good
right no no not at all I'm more to it
than that so I think maybe we should
unpackage define and we should reinvent
virtue as well right what that means
let's let's pick up on something that
everybody's familiar with virtual
reality the virtual world why do we use
that term because the remote the meaning
of virtue is actually a power right it's
a power in act it's a it's a potential
it's not just mere possibility it's
actually a living potential that's being
enacted right it's being actualized so
the virtue of honesty is to have the
potential the set of skills sensibility
and sense of self that when it comes
into a particular situation will be
actualized as courage or actualized as
honesty that's what a virtue means which
explains why the virtues are associated
with the Platonic forms because of
putana forms are these exponent powers
of knowing then the expression knowing
in virtue yes all of a sudden makes a
whole lot of sense
exactly and notice that we do that we
we're knowing in virtue of we're doing
this in virtue of exactly exactly so
what I what I'm trying to do in Andrew
I'm trying to do the I'm trying to do
this thing and I don't know if I'm
succeeding or not it's like an open but
you see what I'm trying instead of just
giving you you know sentences about your
particular question I'm trying to logo's
them together I'm trying to bring them
together so they belong together and
they unfold and they take on a life of
their own and and and and they afford
exploration they afford more discussion
they afford more conversation I'm not
trying to foreclose on anything hmm well
when you were talking about potential
and relating that to virtue I was
thinking about soul again yeah and I was
thinking that the soul is kind of an
echo of the future of your future
potential of the beauty that you could
become yes
but that's well said notice what you've
just done you know when you said you
know this of your potential futures
you're gesturing towards the nor more
Ness but you're talking about what you
could become like so the morning is the
mystery of participation it's how we
unfold into being but the suchness is
the mystery of our individuation how we
become what we particularly are what we
individually are until it's great
insight right is that that's that's that
that's the fundamental grammar the
fundamental tonus of human existence
we're always in tension between
individuation and participation and
beauty is a way in which we enact a and
become virtuous within that tension
within that tension hmm so sorry
actually argues in her book not that
beauty is truth or goodness
she says that beauty and this is one of
her core arguments and inspired what I
was saying here the beauty is basically
where we practice being just and we
practice looking for the truth we
practice the show we Pro she uses these
what she's basically saying is beauty is
where we practice the kind of seeing and
being and talking and thinking that
prepares us for for when you know moral
virtues like honesty or which is perhaps
also an intellectual virtue and also
intellectual virtues like you know you
know wisdom and things like that it
prepares us for both of those it's it's
basically the schoolhouse for both the
intellectual and the moral virtues and
that's what I'm trying to bring back
here because I think she's articulating
something beautiful that was a central
idea in Plato I'm not signed of
counterintuitive to how we think of
beauty we kind of think of beauty as
something primordial that has nothing to
do with yeah you know you know any kind
of moral virtues it's just it's just it
doesn't have moral virtues it's like
it's a it's the it's just a flower it's
it's just bare bare truth that brings up
Han right that brings up on so notice
what what Han sang with the aesthetics
of the smooth right how he said how we
reduce Beauty to things being smooth
right because smooth is comforting it
challenges us in no way no
so what he's and what to use my language
one of his complaints is because he uses
l tara t he says we've lost the more I'm
using my language now but I think it's
perfectly consonant with it we've lost
the mourners of beauty and we're gonna
the pay flows also yes and so we the
smooth to smoothness II he talks about
Jeff Koons and his like balloon his
balloon dogs and they're all they're
they're very cute and they're they're
colorful and but there's obviously
they're not like Rodin they don't have
that gravity right no there's no they
don't have this like intense gravity
that that that that Beauty also has like
it does pull you it doesn't just send
you off into bliss it also brings you
into into the earth as well I think
that's exactly right right so what I was
picking up on and horn is smoothness I
mean think about would like the
smoothness of caress so smoothness marks
out a kind of intimacy but it's intimacy
without challenge it's an intimacy and
this is Hans point it is deadening right
it's deadening because they're the the
way in which beauty right finds the
suchness and the mortis to each other
the educational aspect he deuce to draw
out that's being left out of beauty
that's Hans main completed beauty as a
veil it's not a it's not a it's not
everything being presented to you it's
always behind a veil that's right
because it's always got mourners to it
think about the veil again the veil
again it connotes an intimacy but it
also right there's a beyond this right
there's a there's a way in which it has
the mortise it recedes from you and it
challenges you it draws you forth it
puts a demand on you every disclosure
from it puts a demand on you to go
through transformation to keep in
conformity with what has been disclosed
and that's the training for virtue
that's the training for truth that's the
training for goodness beauty and beauty
is what actually trains us it's like
it's it's the common educational
ancestor of the pursuit of truth and the
pursuit of goodness yeah he also said
Han that within the smooth right we
don't even have a notion of
ugliness anymore that's right there's no
gravity to ugliness either so and it
occurred to me that in order to
understand beauty right we also have to
understand you know the ugliness of our
world you know our the ugliness of when
we depart from beauty like we need that
contrast we need that dialectic we can't
just you know again this is we this is
why you probably mention horror you know
in a sense because there's there there
is there's beauty is is is tearing you
to pieces on some level if it's taken
too far right I and that's what Rilke
said right and I but I think what you're
pointing to Andrew and I'm gonna shut up
so Chris can talk but what I think what
you're pointing to is what I'm trying to
argue for notice that when when you
started bringing in and you if you want
and this is what I think Holly is doing
when you want to bring in that contrast
and you want to enhance it you're
talking about a normativity you're
talking about judgments of there's
something deeply wrong with ugliness
there's something contrast of ly deeply
right and I think the only way we can do
that without parts falling into the seal
definitions is to realign beauty with
virtue again ugliness is conducive to
Vice as virtue is commute eNOS is
conducive to virtue to virtue that's
what I want to say mm-hmm that's gives
it back its gravitas that gives it back
its gravitas I think in order for that
to to be possible that that particular
reinvent EO of beauty it has to be
understood it has to be understood
translate it can't be it has to be a
property of the relation with being and
not a property that presents as an
object of the world right because you
know much of what we consider to be ugly
on its face can be pronounced
beautifully within the right frame of
perspective within a frame of
perspective that is attentive
selectively to certain detail the
ugliness can be bared beautiful you can
see beauty and decay for example
absolutely you can see beauty in the
absolute squalor and but but in that
case beauty beauty is the affinity of
your particular relation to the your
your like I mean I mean that that's why
that's why beauty emerges so so
naturally within dialog because it's a
it's a it's an affined property of the
relation between the eye and the bow and
in the same way that it is and the in
the matrix of the dialogue between
persons so it is between so it is
perceptual II right in terms of your
relationship with your being in the
world itself it's a property of that
relation that you strike well I think
that's exactly right
and I was trying to port n that when I
was talking about it as meta optimal
grip and I'm alluding back to the
previous discussion the three arrows had
about soul as the Faculty of faith where
faith isn't any closure right faith is
actually maintaining right relationship
through change and I think that's what
I'm trying to say beauty is it is
exactly it's it's a faithful right
relationship it's transductive between
you it's not in the eye of the beholder
nor is it in the object but it's it's is
your relationship to the world a
virtuous one or a vicious one that's
right that's right it has to do fine two
renewing when you brought faith in I
thought it's it's renewing your vows
constantly its renew yes yes yes you
know it's exactly that it's I mean we're
exemplifying it here the reinvent yo is
that renewing because we're constantly
trying to breathe new life into these
terms so that we can do exactly what I'm
talking about here who's that right it's
right great mm-hmm that's right that's
right
there's no de logos cannot gain traction
cannot gain any traction in realism
without beauty for that very reason so
it's really interesting because when I
was doing the workshop with people well
because what so what what I when it came
to me Chris it's a practical consequence
of this because I'd always wondered and
you know Cornford and others have made
Sur this weird thing about Socrates
always wondered why the dialogues always
figure on virtues either moral virtues
or intellectual virtues and then I
realized that's not happenstance
that is not happenstance the deal logos
has to always be about the topic of
virtue and it always has to be the
enacted tonus of virtue though that that
is not happenstance that's how you get
the metonymy what you're talking about
is actually right metonymically related
to what you're actually enacting that
that is not a coincidence in this it's a
necessity of the very constitution of
dialectic we have to be talking about a
virtue as we enact it as we and we and
we resonate between there's no other way
right in order in order for the meaning
and the meta meaning to be properly
affined into relation in order to in
order for the in order for the meaning
of the logos to become conversant with
the meaning of the logos the higher
order meaning of the logos that gathers
the entire dialog it you have to start
with its you have to start with this
metonymic child in order to then aspire
to the parent if I can put it that way
no I think that's right so what has been
happening with people other people have
been doing some of these experiments
about trying to bring argumentation and
they just bring in a topic like a
problem and it doesn't go anywhere but
when I told people I meant in the sense
of instruction I said no no this is what
you're gonna do we're gonna break up
into groups of four right and then what
you're gonna do is you're gonna do four
you're gonna choose a virtue and then
one person is gonna begin by saying and
I propose let's say honesty is this and
the other person is going to amplify it
they're gonna say well can you say a
little bit more or I noticed you're
making this gesture they're gonna try
and reveal the beauty of how the person
is enacting it and use that as a as a
scaffold for getting them to say more
and more and more and then the second
person has to come to a place right
where right the first person sort of
said I'm done and the second person says
well this is how this is what I
understood you to be saying and they
have to make sure that they understand
them right they have to the other the
first person has to be heard and then
they have to the second person has to
say what they appreciate about it in the
not only in the sense of understanding
but what was valuable what did they see
that they didn't see before and then
then they have to say what was missing
yeah but was mysterious what went
slightly off and then what they do is
when they and that they do that and they
turn to the next person they do what was
off what was missing and then they make
proposal about what honesty is and you
keep cycling that through people and
then what you do is you get the groups
and you bring all the groups together
and this group is doing courage this
group is doing honesty and you get all
the groups and you say okay now what is
virtue itself and you and you know what
everybody keeps talking about about how
how they were amazed by how this the
topics just exploded and they felt
deeply engaged because they're enacting
and then they're seeing them and then
and and then they're all willing to do
this what normally people say they don't
like to do they're willing to go into
this abstract discussion about what what
is virtue itself it's an agog a that
that's what you're describing is a
simulation of the an agogic process well
it's a simulation of both the
sensibility transcendence and the an
agog a because when you're doing that
into that yeah appreciation that's the
sensibility transcend I'm not sure if I
understand that the term an agog II I'm
sorry before can you clarify that just a
little bit what you mean by an agogic
yeah yeah G is like making an analogy no
no although I think for all kinds of
reasons they're deeply they're deeply
interpenetrating but know what I mean by
a nagashi is the kind of the dis the
ascent to theosis that's associated with
graduate orders of ontological
abstractions so that would Plato talks
about that that the questing eros
ventures from beautiful bodies to
beautiful customs to beautiful ideas
it's the reciprocal opening that's also
a kind of ontological transcendence
right right and so the idea then being
that the reciprocal opening that happens
interpersonally between die ologists
symbolizes the process of the reciprocal
opening that happens ana goggly in your
relationship with the world itself that
somehow those two logos and Agoge is the
trend trance continual transcendent
movements yes yes okay and let's say and
then there's the other movement which is
the grounding movement where do you what
would you call that that's that's the
intimacy that's the sensibility
transcendence I really getting really
mutually fitted to each other really
mutually fitting each other more and
more and more
right so and that's where the
amplification process it's like
breathing in and breathing out and it's
very much so nicely we're smiling I mean
that you know before it became an
ambitious term that's what conspiring
meant it meant to breathe together right
which is which is also why you know
which is also white you know the diet
the diagnosis of despair as Kierkegaard
figured it had everything to do with
asphyxiation and hyperventilation right
not being able to get a purchase on your
relation your proper relation with being
the the particular sickness of the soul
that is despair is precisely not being
able anymore to respire in this this new
language now john respire between your
suchness and morna's yeah exactly
exactly so then the reinvent yo the
processor then this this anamnesis of
reinvent eeeh that were undertaking is
in some ways a process of renewing and
renewing our respiration britta bringing
breath you know into the everything
breathing life would be the more yeah
and that's the original metaphor for a
souling right yeah yeah cuz the soleus
all souls is related to the breath isn't
it right the Numa yeah Numa very much ya
know when people were in this practice
like of course it was the first time I
did it and you know I you know
dialectics should be you know on top of
a whole bunch of other practical ecology
of practices and there should be a whole
educational program before you get into
it but in there so Daniel it's the first
time so it's very clunky in a lot of
ways but nevertheless the way people
were clearly resonating the mourners and
the suchness and they were willing like
they were getting they were suddenly get
caught up in the beauty of it and and
you know and it was interesting to see
how people would say start the they're
starting to catch in the light of their
eyes wait wait you know and because it's
making its making virtue come alive to
them but not as a topic but but as a way
of being right it was very it was very
exciting and a multi-dimensional way of
being rather than just you know however
whatever
are very reductive versions of all of
these concepts are um I guess when you
enter into their aliveness that's pretty
that's exciting that's like okay wow
there's there's life here it's not it's
not just you know a world of dead dead
language or something it's exactly and
notice the Popo Antechinus you could
feel the poetry of it right
exactly it's police's know they like
think about when a poet I mean I read
poetry right when you win you're writing
poetry it's exactly that process of like
like that that it's reinvent you because
as you're speaking these words you
discover a fought in them that correct
that comes back to you from the words
like that's what's happening when you're
doing poesis and and notice that the
connection that that's the connection
you were intuiting Andrew between the
aliveness the insolvent and the beauty
we're doing all of those together but
these are just three different aspects
of the very same thing mm-hmm
it also happens not only when you're
doing when you're writing poetry but
when you're writing dramatically happens
right because the whole probe the whole
process of rendering character is
precisely that you're giving such a form
to the two to wait like you're you're
embodying the virtue and in the
embodiment of the virtue as such you're
giving it a particular formal a
particular particular the formalization
in context of virtue
I think emerges as character no that's
great yeah that's so important we really
need to bring we need to reinvent arts
as well because we need to bring
narrative art back in absolutely and
it's yes that's how we embody the a lot
of these things that's how we go to the
next level perhaps yeah that's one form
of gathering the logos right gathering
the logos is precisely the process of
dramatic characterization you play
through in an exploratory fashion you
play through the embodiment of virtue
and that's why deep deep forms of
characterization are justly
graded because they disclose and
unconcealed dimensions of being in
virtue that are otherwise unavailable to
us that's what good that's what good
storytelling does that's why we Revere
good storytelling is because it it
immerses us it immerses us in an
embodied enacted fashion into the
morning in virtue this connection
between character which is the Faculty
of virtue and characterization and drama
that's brilliant Chris I hadn't thought
about that that's exactly right you know
that Keith Utley he's a he's one of my
colleagues at the University of Toronto
is all this research showing that you
know working with drama working with
literature is our primary way of
training ourselves to be more virtuous
absolutely yeah yeah which also means it
doesn't mean again I'm trying to get
away from this sentimental idea of verse
because because in drop drama is usually
about going into the human darkness
right going into the horrors right it's
often that way I mean a tragedy is that
right in any case you know Kurtz goes
into the the EC's the horror the horror
and that's what Marvel's so there's been
it's not just beauty as as some kind of
really terrible sort of like sentimental
version of reality it's something else
but look but look at what I always want
to bring gravity to these concepts when
we talk about them because because they
have become because you know if it
becomes so Disneyland yeah yeah where
virtue is the power to lead a good life
in all the dimensions of goodness that's
what virtue is it doesn't mean the
moralistic you know think the following
rules right I'm thinking of you know I
want to live the kind of life that
Socrates led or the Buddha led or Jesus
of Nazareth led and that can't be
captured or reduced to following this
rule or that ruler or this rule well
it's an adventure isn't it it's an
adventure to look out to look beyond
right and think about Marlowe in the
heart of darkness and think about the
beauty of Conrad's prose
I know the heart of darkness is
contentious because of colonialism
racism I'm gonna put that aside because
that's another thing to talk about but
in I mean think about what Marlowe
represents Marlowe represent virtue in
the face right of this he because he
practices self-restraint and he that's
not reducible to any sort of fruit you
know he's not a prude he's not just
adopting you know a moralistic set of
rules he's constantly continuing the
journey he keeps good faith in that
sense with Kurtz but he he dedicates
himself to remaining right true to his
humanity he practices he keeps talking
about self-restraint he doesn't get
swallowed by by the horrors but but he
doesn't he doesn't avert his gaze either
I remember like what was it Kurosawa
when he was a kid he walked through
Tokyo after the earthquake and there
were corpses everywhere and his brother
said his brother said look look you have
to look because because you know you
know the poet doesn't avert his eyes or
yeah
Marlow I think Marlow finds a sweet spot
I thought I'm talking about mm-hmm he's
he but he's also but he's the
self-restraint as he maintains that
intimacy with himself he meet he does
his sickness and he maintains those two
and that is what actually affords him
going on the journey the quest and and
and how does he like one of the ways
formally in which he does all of that is
think about the form of the novella
itself he's relaying the story to a
chorus of of onlookers bearing witness
to the very to the very character that
he's conveying right that's a story with
a story
yeah that's why that particular device
the in framing of the story with its I
mean we were talking in our last
conversation together we were talking
about the function of the heavenly host
to the choral function of the the the
mornin of the choral function of
of witnessing transcendently without
being enclosed by the the perspective of
the character that's playing through and
that and that the way that the novella
structured lends that kind of
higher-order perspective that sees the
narrative in virtue of its possibility
of its possible implications of its
possible meaning beyond its meaning
because he relays the story to the
people on the boat right and they're and
they're not saying anything they're just
being they're silent but there's they're
bearing silent witness to the very
dynamic that he's exemplified and so is
the reader because the story starts
reading personal narrator and then takes
you into that yeah that's right there's
all the playing with that framing that's
really good that's a great observation
Chris but well I mean it's tipped to
your point and you to Andrew it's like
that there's a reason why and there's a
there's a reason why there's such
sublimity to that and similar narratives
it's it's precise and it's precisely
there inexhaustibility right that that
the way in which they enact that the the
narrative as such in acts patterns that
intimate the morning the narrative as
such and then that more nests beyond the
narrative s such as precisely what is
enclosed and borne out by the witnessing
presence that surrounds it both the
reader and perhaps the ancillary
characters and onlookers and that's why
right Conrad has Marlow and he says that
that the Marlow is sitting there like a
Buddha at the end right oh that's that's
in the dark too by the way
dark well yeah yeah yeah yeah I guess
then there's the scene where the Buddha
meets Mara or something and and is is
him exactly exactly
you know he's mmm
so man drew all right this is my attempt
to was not like I say I wanted to way of
like Ken we bring when somebody is
asking us questions can we reinvent you
argumentation not as I'm gonna like
establish things but what I'm gonna do
is logos I'm gonna try and gather a
whole bunch of things together so they
belong together they sing together they
start to beautify each other and then
they afford discourse and discussion and
involvement that's what I'm trying
that's why I'm trying to reinvent EO
argumentation here mmm the making of
proposals and the consideration of how
they stick together and belong together
beyond just logical coherence I was also
saying go go ahead Chris um I was just
gonna say it's interesting because one
of the things that happens is when you
bring you bring these you bring these
particular definitions in proximity to
one another they okay I'm going to
personify them for a minute but I don't
think it's inappropriate to given all a
discussion about character they begin to
the virtues when they're brought into
within range of one another
allow us to see they allow us to to I
mean the the the way in which they
become an conversant is that the virtues
begin to know in virtue of one another
yes right so the so so so one virtue
begins to know in virtue of its of its
neighboring virtue and is then so in is
then so articulated it's it's a virtue
knowing in virtue of another virtue
which sounds like a mouthful but
essentially at once you bring these
things into proximity they begin to know
by means of one another and in being so
known by means of one another
they're the shared reflections of depth
begin to appreciate this is a point in
both the Neoplatonic Western tradition
and the Buddhist teaching tradition so
the minutes indras net right yes you've
mentioned that in one here I think I
think Andrew you mentioned that in one
of our previous yeah Nations everything
is reflected in everything anything is
reflected at faith is reflected in soul
which is reflected in virtue
which is reflected right they all become
eyes unto the world yeah and the
Platonists says right that all of the
forms are have exactly that relationship
to each other they're all like indras
Nets they're all reflect and each one
captures the mornin its own particular
suchness and but it for bright for us it
has to unfold in time but for in you
know for Platonists that's that's
happening sort of in eternity and the
logos of eternity that sort of
holographic intelligibility we have to
try and capture it in the sequential
logos of speech as best we can and
that's exactly what so that metaphor is
exactly the resident metaphor the way
that virtue speak to me Chavez speaks
right the ground of intelligibility
itself which is then again echoes with
the analogy of the dialogic practice of
the two conversation partners so as as
we as we do as we do between ourselves
as conversation partners so then do the
virtues in forgive each other
exactly exactly I like that turn of
phrase the virtues in virtue of each
other
that's beautiful Chris the way you do
that is so impressive well I'm just I'm
just riffing off of you riffing is
exactly the right thing as of this the
Jazz of this is you know constitutive of
its beautification it's not just riffing
it's integral to what we're doing here
and and that was what's really a and
when when we did the workshop and you
got to people at the end they were
riffing off their own particular virtue
that they discussed courage or honesty
but they were they were jazzing they
were they were finding resonance and
convergence right and divergence but in
a harmonious fashion between each other
they were doing with the deep learning
they were converging and varying and
converging and varying it was beautiful
yeah hmm and and sometimes you know I
like it when some jazz music just falls
apart
psychedelic music or sometimes you know
what I like I listen to these like the
Grateful Dead they just fall apart in
the whole band just disassembles itself
completely and and then they kind of
find their way back to each other oh
yeah I think that's an interesting
process that the falling apart and
coming back back together like we're
covering from aporia yeah instead of
going always for the high right yeah
music is always like an orgasmic trying
to be an academic type of experience or
complete orgasmic bars whereas the the
Jazz is a deeper thing because it
doesn't always go for the peak right it
it falls into the valleys in it that's
beautiful
you know it did it lingers like and
that's another word that Han uses I
think yeah there lingeringly when it
comes to beauty it lingers awhile and
then it just it's lets itself go and
then it and then it becomes intense
again and but that's that's the Emporia
as criticality you know in
self-organizing systems they get stuck
and what you have to do is you have to
put you have to lifters
you have to perturb them you have to
disturb them yeah right they get to a
point of criticality where they're
almost breaking apart falling apart and
only venture them or something doctor or
me a puncture is the word that came to
mind yes equilibrium
yeah when you were when you were
describing initially John you're open
precis but you know the the equilibrium
between the suchness and and the more
nasai think of the the complexify
assimilation and the medic and the medic
combination that you talk about within
within the cognitive science
nomenclature and it sounds like virtue
and fans again maps are more or less
identical it does I think virtue is very
much about sort of getting that's what
it's a meta optimal grip on right meta
assimilation and met accommodation right
totally and that for those of you who
are watching I mean this is discussed at
length in some of the videos within my
within awakening for the meeting crisis
and in some of the stuff that Chris and
I have written I think we talked about
this in the zombie book don't we do we I
don't know I don't know how I don't
think we get we I don't think we get too
- deeply into the thief in cognitive
science vocabulary but yeah it's in
there somehow yeah do you guys know that
the work of Rene Girard because one of
my question for from before John was and
one of my thoughts about what beauty is
it's beyond mimetic desire on some level
it's it's when you when you when you
experience uniqueness that is beyond
imitation of some kind it goes on this
sort of and that's what we're kind of
looking for because we're always trapped
in a memetic Hall of Mirrors on some
level we're always we're copying each
other and we're we're stumbling around
with with concepts at least I am and and
then and we kind of break through and
then we have this fresh moment that's
that's that's beyond yeah mimetic desire
does that does Matt does that make any
sense makes total slips and Gerrard's
thing I think is it apropos here and his
idea of you know of Jesus on undermining
like Jesus being the criticality and
think about the word critical in crisis
and cross and how they're all related
Jesus being the criticality that
disturbs that that whole memetics self
enclosure I think that that's exactly
right because right that's so the thing
to do is remember that there's always
not always silent but often silent
partner because if Gerard is I mean his
prototypical instance of what you're
talking about mimetic desire is
covetousness right it's envy or jealousy
right Envy yeah he said Envy is the most
hidden desire the one we don't admit to
ourselves so we're we're always being
dragged around right and V so compare
envy to admiration which is a virtue
what is it when you admire somebody and
you don't envy them right is it you
instant so think about arrows as so when
I want to be one with someone I can
reduce that to consumption I'm gonna be
one by consuming you more it can be a
narrow us that is turning its face
towards agape I'm I'm gonna generative
as because Plato says I'm gonna generate
beauty within Beauty right so I'm going
to try and create a life that you know
that is in some relevant sense similar
to Socrates but not Socrates mmm it's my
I'm not
take from Socrates on trying to generate
in admiration and so I think this is
exactly what we're talking about here
right if we have a beauty that's just a
smooth that is just the act of
assimilation consuming making it one
with me in no way disturbing me in no
way being a critical moment for me but
if I have genuine beauty then I'm going
to be drawn beyond myself yeah
but the critical moment also is
recognize recognizing one's Envy at
times rather than just trying to aspire
to to an ideal you know state of
admiration is that that we notice that
we feel that in that way a time but that
but that's exactly the point
right it this is to add to what you're
saying about how we're trying to
reinvent your virtue
Socratic virtue is always inseparably
bound up with self-knowledge right and
it's the kind of its this is this is one
of the great Socratic insights there's
aspects of myself that I can't know by
introspection or even reflection I can
only know them in interaction with you
because they call forth both the
potential for virtue and vice in me then
I can't call forth of myself or make
available to myself but if I pay
attention if I come in good faith to the
dialog I can become aware of my Envy and
I can open myself up to a different
possibility therein yeah because at that
point moment you're no longer seeing
through you're no longer seeing and
knowing by means of your envi when it
becomes opaquely knowable to you as such
possibility of transcending it becomes
then available right by knowing it maybe
that's a bit like the shadow as well
isn't it about absolutely yeah yeah
shadows by how you put you have to pay
it if you just think you didn't your
shadow by just doing active imagination
and sitting inside your room you have
missed Jung's point you're going to get
your shadow when you realize how you're
projecting onto other people
yeah it's only when you recognize your
projections and hear the other person's
right what way but here the other person
behind when you projected on them when
you open up to the other nostalgia
projection so they can break through the
projection then and only then do you
realize your projection yes and then the
process of doing that could just they
become dialectical of course of course
so so the beauty is is perhaps also a
moment of deep sincerity right rather
than let's say it's a pretension or yeah
a totally totally
I mean that so you know Socratic
humility is important I think that's the
proper I we talked about this last time
the proper response to beauty is
reverence and Brett reverence has
humility within it right
it's reverence is is this bidirectional
realization there's right there you
recognize who you are there's an
intimacy with who you are and there's
also a recognition of the mourners
beyond you that can nevertheless afford
your transformation and and beauty
beauty is such - that it it even as it
even if even as it contra distinguishes
your supreme inadequacy it also saves
you from it it heals you and it rescues
you from the interminable death at the
same time it is it is it it inflicts
upon you death without without the
undying death yeah yeah that makes me
think of Ulysses you know there's the
Homeric version of Allah sees and then
there's James Joyce Ulysses and the
character is so flawed he's he's so
human right so we have this ideal and
then we have our you know both those
things and he becomes the hero just to
his mmm I don't know I guess there was
that authenticity on someone the the
yeah that's just what came to mind when
you were speaking about this yeah no I
like that I think that fits very well so
so what about the specific proposal of
because we because there's also a
specific proposal I made about under
which is part of the reinvent EO of
beauty and also simultaneously the re
inventor of virtue to see virtue as the
beauty of wisdom and this is a different
way I'm trying to propose a different
way of thinking about both virtue and
beauty in light of or in virtue of
wisdom itself what do you think about
that as a proposal because it's always
been mysterious to me in Plato
when he talks about the beauty of virtue
and why we should care about it and why
it's superior to sensual beauty but if
it's a way in which we refine to wisdom
itself then I can understand why it
should matter to us so much I think it
makes it existentially available it
provides an entree into wisdom what's
that is ordinarily the the sohe entre
virtue the virtue right so the V because
virtue is both speakable and possessive
all its participa
white it straddles both levels of
signification so you can speak about
virtue that's right and you can inhabit
virtue and my body virtue and so because
of that it provides a kind of access it
provides a kind of it provides a way to
inhabit beauty so when you were talking
about the the idea of that that that
beauty when being in right relation to
beauty is such that you can't you can't
have a consumptively memetic
relationship to it which i think is a
profound point and yet also being in
right relation to beauty is somehow also
mimetic in the sense that is that
mimesis of that which is not imitatable
i don't know if that's a word imitatable
let's go with it if if
mimesis of that which is not able to be
imitated is precisely what induces the a
poetic experience oh and there's
something about inhabiting the virtue
that is a a and it's an effort and it's
like it's an effort to imitate that
which is in them inimitable that's what
imitable it is it is the imitation of
that which is inimitable and that is
precisely what induces the Apple Rhea
but but the attempt to embody the virtue
makes available the a poetic experience
that is beautiful in its nature is that
why you would wear masks in theatre and
in a sense yeah yeah I think that yes
yes absolutely
because you're trying to imitate
something the beauty of doing that
that's beyond you on some level
absolutely I mean theater but also I
plain I think of literacy as well write
in a more overtly religious sense right
you are trying to imitate that which is
inimitable you're trying to you're
trying to effect a gesture toward a
meaning that cannot be espoused in
gesture and yet the precise that kind of
a poetic effort you're teetering on the
precipice of intelligibility at that
moment but precisely that at that that
precarious point that precarious edge
that that beauty walks that as John
described at that optimal balance of
beauty between the horrific and the
confirmed I have to admit I'm having a
hard time connecting beauty to wisdom
those two things don't don't go together
for me on some level
well perhaps again this is my more
romantic disposition because I always
think that it's it's when you cast off
when you cast off any pretense of wisdom
or non wisdom it's it's just a full full
embrace of some kind but well some
wisdom feels to me wisdom feels to me a
step removed of God does that make any
sense
for us perhaps this is me being
argumentative no this is a good point
this is a good this is a good point I
think I think so maybe one place to
start is that beauty beauty becomes a
way of effecting profound changes in our
advertent attention right Beauty is what
calls out and directs our attention and
attention can be subject to all kinds of
self-deceptive patterns patterns that
recur patterns that are enshrined and
entrenched into forceable habituated
modes of being or modes of having I
suppose and what Beauty does is it
somehow Beauty can debilitate those
patterns precisely because it can
recover our attention and repurpose it
and refocus it so I think maybe that's
one way to start is that I think of
beauty as like the Herald of wisdom
right it's what calls our attention to
it it's not necessarily identical with
it but it is the very thing that it is
the very thing that draws out aspiration
because it's capable of of laying waste
to the particular patterns by which we
see and know at any given point like the
sirens that are calling to like the
sirens right which is a great example of
how it can be used Cyclops versus the
call Ulysses to his doom and somehow he
has to make it home to us that's right
to his wife who has been surrounded by
suitors and all that so it's like yeah
so so yeah there's always this I get
beauty is is is bound up in seduction
and pathless right but it's also bound
up in insight mm-hmm right and like we
talked about this last time about the
machinery and the attentional machinery
of beauty is also the same machinery
especially if there's been criticality
in it right you have to break out of a
frame right that that being struck by
beauty there's an insight and and so if
we if we get
training of attention and the affording
of insight these are integral to the
cultivation of wisdom they're integral
to the cultivation of wisdom that's I
mean that's why you know that's why
meditative practices have been
associated with the cultivation of
wisdom yeah it's precisely what you're
doing is training attention and
affording insight yeah yeah yeah yeah it
allows you to spew tea somehow the onset
of beauty allows you to recast you to
recast your your recast the mode the
fort recast reform of life forecast your
mode of being in relation mm-hmm I think
if we think of it as a fundamental
relational dynamic then it can reach can
refigure the way in which that is framed
for you at any given moment you must
change your life you must change your
life okay says that's what Beauty does
it tells us you know very directly that
you know something some radical shift is
necessary that's true virtue is the
ability to appropriate with to take
responsibility to appropriately respond
to how every true disclosure was a true
demand on you disclosure demand is
exactly proportioning the relationship
between more nests and suchness which is
what I propose to you what beauty is and
I think insofar as we're trying to get
the Sophia of wisdom and the furnaces of
wisdom that's virtue and that's a kind
of beauty verge she was a regulation of
beauty hmm I get struck by beauty in a
sense yeah and then the virtue is is how
you navigate that pathos how do you
navigate that I would say so I would say
that that thing that is that that can
bring out all the you know the demons in
you and and and also bring out your most
heroic soulful being right it can it can
it can do both I think so and this is
what Plato I mean so right philosophy
are is the virtue
of what it's the appropriate virtue to
the experience of wonder and Reverend
just like reverence Woodruff argues is
the appropriate virtue for the you know
for the experience of aw hmm but is but
as philosophy uh is philosophy em what
among the virtues Jean or is it the
harmony of the virtues themselves well
and I think of philosophy a-- and a
higher order sense i think of it as the
orchestration of the virtues oh it is i
think it's its but but philosophy of
begins in wonder wonder has a special
role for philosophy Oh tonic vision
because wonder is exactly the moment of
what we've been talking about its the
moment of so if we compare if we it's
very if we contrast wonder to curiosity
where curiosity is there's something
missing and I want to have it you know
which is good but where wonder is I'm
willing to call myself in my world into
question there can be no pursuit it's
it's a wonder has I think in a special
role I think you're right philosophy is
about all of the virtues but to use your
term I think wonder is the entree it is
the right right philosophy of first of
all is the virtue of appropriately
wondering because if we can't call
ourself and our world into question none
of the other virtues are attainable for
us mmm-hmm
can I throw another formulation here
just for yep just for fun
but in the Buddhist tradition you have
sutrayana which is about renunciation
it's about training in moral virtue and
it's about you know it's about taming
and controlling your emotions and
desires and and becoming becoming wise
and compassionate in the world and then
the next level tantrayana you step into
another kind of world which which isn't
isn't it's no longer it's no longer
process of training it's it's it's more
like you're hit directly by the by the
energies and so so those two things so
and of course once you enter tone triana
you also have to to
to have embodied suit Rihanna like you
have to become a morally virtuous person
before you can you can you can wrestle
with those those more direct energies
it's deeply analogous to the Neoplatonic
ascent right so the the Latinas has you
nobody calls the civic virtues which is
the virtues and you know this is the
virtue of being you know living with
others what we normally call the moral
virtues but they're much more like we
said here the understanding that this is
that the even the moral virtues are not
purely individual projects they have to
be done in community and in concert with
other people and then you have what he
calls you know the cathartic or the
purging virtues these are the virtues
that take you beyond moral virtue
because now what you're trying to do is
not you're not trying to be honest or be
good you're trying to see that about
which the depths of you and the depths
of a reality afford this there's this is
a trans moral sense of goodness and this
is what takes you to also you can always
thinking rational trans rational yes
exactly exactly that's exactly what it
is input - that's exactly what it is you
take you take the you take rational or
what we could call here argumentation as
far as it goes and what it's done is
it's basically a scaffold that brings
you up to a place where you can now see
and be opened up that you can so I think
of it like building a structure have you
ever been in one of the pyramids in the
Mayan jungles you climb up the pyramid
and the point of the structure is to get
to a place where you you you are struck
in a way you can't be struck when you're
in the forest and you're open to calling
yourself in your world into question mmm
argumentation is the building of the
pyramid but when you can then be open to
the sky and to the forest below you and
you're willing to call everything now
into question that is that is that
moving from you logic propositional sort
of understanding of things to a more
spontaneous and let's say dynamic it's
moving and doing of things respectable
and participatory art is it yeah
it's like the teleological suspension of
the ethical perfect although I think it
moves more into beauty does it does it
does beauty becomes more more beauty and
play you become become more important
where in the beginning you're just
slugging away and trying to understand
and you've got your machete and you're
cutting your way through the jungle and
yeah
but the thing you have to remember is is
there's a I mean for and this goes back
to back to the stuff we were saying
earlier about how beauty you know how it
kills you in resurrection like you know
you could you're never gonna become a
God in Plato at most you're always gonna
be godlike and and and you come out of
the clave and see the Sun but you were
turning back into the cave so the
moments in my practice where I touch the
one or the Sun or the ground of being
they then feed back into when I'm doing
the right the propositional or very sort
of thing right no yeah and of course I
think of that then you know the comes
back to the marketplace with yeah
exactly
you know what's called I forget that you
know there's in you know the the Zen
parables were where he you know he's
he's chasing the the bull and then he's
looking for he's riding the Ox and then
and then and then there's nothing
there's emptiness and then he comes back
with with gifts yeah exactly so you know
so you know those moments those moments
of trans rational they they shine into
they in power they install they in live
and they beautify the rational moments
and then the rational moments have
appropriate reverence to what is
disclosed in the trans rational moments
okay that's nice mmm-hmm although I
guess I guess for someone like Allard
that the entire process we've just
described is rationality per se well
yeah the aspiration to rationality and
the aspiration to trans rationality is
itself proleptic rationality and yeah so
far as we're aspiring to any even beat
not even just a virtue but
- Andrew said - something that is beyond
virtue right the good beyond moral
goodness
I think we're engaged in in in some kind
of proleptic process yes for sure yeah
generally we were engaged in aspiration
and the other thing I was thinking about
is how normally think of beauty as
something very high high up there yeah
very sublime and we're very very up here
you know it's it's it's associated with
high culture and and you know all that
sort of stuff but it's also you can find
beauty in a rap song you can find beauty
everywhere like easily and the lowest
you know and in the most you know banal
things it's it's not something that is
necessarily hierarchical or isn't that
the same for virtue mmm we find virtue
in our highest ideals but if that's
useless if you can't find it in my new
show of your life mm-hmm right yeah well
yeah it's like that it's it's like the
in the way that the well not by analogy
by identity the way the Neoplatonic
hypostasis are dispersed ontologically
dispersed without somehow being
diminished yeah right yeah the Sun
shines but it doesn't but it's not
diminished by it's shining yeah even
though he says that's not true but I get
I get but I get platonist as metaphor at
least in exhaustion who cares about the
physics the one overflows or or or or
like the top HN right the the Dow is a
well that you can get you and you can
just continually draw forth from it yeah
yes mm-hmm yes I should get going soon
gentlemen and I think we've seen me to
fall into kind of a wonderful convivial
silence anyways yeah yeah there's a
silence descending on the conversation
somewhat I agree and it's a good one
though it's a really wonderful one so
what are we getting we've reinvented
beauty and we've reinvented the soul and
so what are we gonna and we've
reinvented virtue so what are we going
to reinvent next well like I said I've
been trying to reinvent
rationality and night-night today I was
trying to bring them together with
reinventing argumentation within
dialectic I just want to keep going
because great synthesis John
incidentally like there was a fantastic
theoretical synthesis that you opened
with very very well thank you for that I
mean I'm trying like I said I'm trying
to get what would die illogical
argumentation look like rather than
monological argumentation and I'm trying
to get more the sense of logos as
drawing together the affording insight
that moves you to the next proposal the
draws together like it's different than
just premise premise premise but it's
embodied in feeling isn't it it's it's
it's broadened into the the entire realm
of feeling in an body rather than just
upstairs very much very much it goes
back to your metropolis thing we try to
link hand and heart and head together
right
in this sense of argumentation and so
I'm trying to in soul and and heartening
and and you know make make beautiful all
of these things because notice that we
were willing I mean we came in good
faith and we were willing to probe and
push and move and challenge but all that
did was afford right it just afforded
more and more and more and that's again
III and like I'm I'm working my way
towards this I I'm not complained I'm
not claiming anything complete hearing
but trying to get what this would look
like for us yeah well it's it's I also
want say Andrew that it's very helpful
because John and I John and I do this
all the time and because there's a
certain shorthand and there's a certain
shared vocabulary yeah one thing that
you introduced that we don't really have
as much on our own is you introduce the
kind of more the more sort of
interrogative challenge that's actually
very helpful which it diminishes it
diminishes a little bit because once you
become very very very fluent and how
conversant you are with another person
once this is such a shared once there's
there's so much of a shared vocabulary
that things become
you you you don't realize how like when
up won't clairvoyance or so engine
yeah when John I speak just the two of
us there's we're standing on so many
unspoken presumptions and so many sort
of shared axioms that a lot goes
unchallenged simply because there's
there's there's so much you know there's
so much underfoot that sort of goes
unacknowledged but one thing that you
add to this one of the many things you
add to this is that you challenge some
of those some of those presumptions used
to challenge some of those sort of those
those unspoken premises that were
standing on without realizing that we're
standing on them whether they be having
to do with vocabulary or having to do
with the use of certain terms etc and
that's very very helpful to in the
proper sense of the term to humiliate
the conversation and we're all it into
proper question and you I think you
bring that beautifully and very and very
definitely and I think you guys are
really teaching me something here about
about listening and finding that the
right moment to interject and I do feel
like I'm stumbling around a lot of the
time but but a bit less so I feel like
there's a harmony coming into these
conversations that that that you know
each time that that's a little bit and
that just kind of strikes me and makes
me you know go wow you know that's
amazing you know something is really
happening here to me so so so what you
were saying about dialogue owes being
this process where something is being
brought out of you that you you that you
couldn't find on your own I think that's
happening to me so yeah yes that feels
that feels really exciting yeah yeah and
in a lie that was maybe the most
important thing that was just said over
this whole Congress what you just said
there for me that's exemplifying
everything that I'm trying to bring to
life what you just said that community
golden moment what you just said
so thank you for that oh well thank you
guys so much here here